Guide to the Adelphi Academy and Adelphi College collection 1985.059
Brooklyn Historical Society
Adelphi Academy and Adelphi College collection
1864-1965
Brooklyn Historical Society
Adelphi Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Adelphi College
1985.059
2.25 Linear Feet in five manuscript boxes
Adelphi Academy is a private preparatory school founded in 1863 by Dr. Edward S. Bunker and Aaron Chadwick. This collection documents the development and evolution of the Academy's curriculum, its physical growth and infrastructural development in its early years, and student life. It also documents Adelphi College prior to its becoming Adelphi University in 1963.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The source and date of acquisition for this collection are largely unknown. The majority of the collection was formally accessioned in 1985. A smaller portion was removed from the Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006) and the Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007). The 1906 catalog was the gift of Marcia Hendrie Holroyd, 1990.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series by institution. Within each series, the materials are arranged by type and roughly chronologically.
Historical note
Adelphi Academy is a private preparatory school founded in 1863 by Dr. Edward S. Bunker and Aaron Chadwick, who had both previously taught at the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute. Though the Academy made its start as a school for boys, it became coeducational in 1867. It was officially incorporated and chartered by the Board of Trustees of the City of Brooklyn in 1869, and grew steadily throughout the 19th century, reaching its peak enrollment of 1,291 students in 1891. The Academy's original location was at 412 Adelphi Street, but due to its steady growth, it gradually outgrew this space and moved to newly built facilities at the corner of Lafayette Avenue and St. James Place in 1868.
Since as early as 1871, Adelphi Academy's administrators had considered the possibility of establishing a liberal arts college to be affiliated with the Academy. In 1896, under the administration Dr. Charles Herbert Levermore, Adelphi College (later Adelphi University) was chartered by the State of New York. Its original location was in a building directly behind the Academy at the corner of St. James Place and Clifton Place. Though they operated as separate institutions, Adelphi Academy and Adelphi College remained closely connected, with many of the Academy's students matriculating to the College upon graduation.
In 1929, Adelphi College moved its campus to Garden City, Long Island and was granted university status by the State of New York in 1963. Due to steadily declining enrollment, Adelphi Academy moved from its location at Lafayette Avenue and St. James Place to a smaller facility in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1965. As of 2023, both institutions continue to operate in the same locations.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Brooklyn Yearbook collection (BCMS.0031)
Brooklyn photograph and illustration collection (ARC.202) - Subject: Schools
Scope and Contents
The Adelphi Academy collection measures 2.25 linear feet and spans the dates 1864 to 1965. The collection documents the development and evolution of the Academy's curriculum, its physical growth and infrastructural development in its early years, as well as student life. Included in the collection are a narrative history of the Academy covering the period from its founding through the early 20th century; documents pertaining to the construction of the Academy's original building on Adelphi Street and its incorporation; course catalogs (including a complete run from 1899 to 1942); yearbooks; and copies of the student newspaper. It also contains catalogs, yearbooks, and a booklet from the Academy's peer institution, Adelphi College.
Catalogs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Private schools |z New York (State) |z New York; Local histories; School yearbooks; Annual reports; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Adelphi Academy (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Adelphi College
- Adelphi Academy
  - Catalogs, 1866-1868, 1869-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Catalogs, 1870-1872, 1873-1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Catalogs, 1880, 1881, 1888-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs, 1891-1892, 1893-1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Catalogs, 1901, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Academy Record, 1864-1868 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Erection of new building, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incorporation and Recent History booklet, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Event programs, 1870-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Inaugural Exercises for Homer Sprague as Principal (1870), Founder's Day (1890), and an alumni party and reunion (1914 and 1919 respectively).
  - Ephemera, 1870-circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes preliminary announcement (1870), a printed image of the school building in 1868, text about the school from the Brooklyn Advance, and a map and aerial image of the school's playing field.
  - Fundraising appeal booklet, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Adelphian journal, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Adelphian journal, 1905-1906, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Adelphian journal, 1933, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Adelphic yearbook, 1891, 1907-1911 (Box 2, Folder 3-7)
  - Commencement programs, 1892, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Adelphi Post, 1932, 1949, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Adelphi News, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Anniversary publications, 1938, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes materials from the school's 75th and 125th anniversaries and the cover of the centennial publication.
  - Handbook, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Adelphi Oracle newspaper, 1965 (Box OS-31)
- Adelphi College
  - The Adelphi booklet, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Catalogs, 1899-1909, 1910, 1913-1915, 1920-1922, 1923-1928, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
  - Catalogs, 1931-1942, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Oracle yearbook, 1908, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)